A Guide to the Virginia Junior Academy of Science Records, 1931-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Virginia Junior Academy of Science Records, 1931-1999
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1981-094
15.4 cu. ft. 11 boxes
The Virginia Junior Academy of Science Records include correspondence (including some correspondence antedating the founding of the VJAS); notes and minutes from committees and general meetings, reports, publications, memorabilia, and subject files.
Virginia. Junior Academy of Sciences.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The intial Virginia Junior Academy of Science Records were donated to Special Collections in 1981. Additional donations occurred through 1999.
Historical Information
The Virginia Academy of Science (VAS) organized the first Virginia Junior Academy of Science (VJAS) meeting in 1941, after several years of discussions about how best to discover and promote scientific aptitude in the secondary schools of Virginia. Though the VJAS ceased to meet during World War II, it was reorganized after the war. Beginning in 1946, the VAS sponsored a statewide science competition for high school students known as the Virginia Science Talent Search. Since 1952, a VJAS newspaper (the Junior Science Bulletin) has been published; and since 1963 the Virginia Junior Academy of Science Proceedings have served as a record of papers presented at VJAS meetings.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Junior Academy of Science Archives include correspondence (including some correspondence antedating the founding of the VJAS); notes and minutes from committees and general meetings, reports, publications, memorabilia, and miscellaneous files.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by chronologically in subject files.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Virginia Academy of Science Records, 1920-1999, Ms1981-096. Finding aid available online. Note: This collection is in off-site storage and requires 2-3 days notice for retrieval. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Virginia. Junior Academy of Sciences.
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Science and Technology
Contents List
- Records, 1931-1979 (Bulk 1931-1964) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence about founding a junior academy, 1931-1940
  - Historic photos, documents, etc., used in VJAS history exhibits, 1940-1947
  - AAAS awards, 1940-1965
  - VAS honorary membership awards, 1940-1974
  - Historical information on awards, etc., 1941-1968
  - Historic files, correspondence, etc., 1942-1960
  - E. C. L. Miller award recipients, 1943-1963
  - History and general information, 1943-1965
  - Major Catesby Jones award recipients, 1943-1963
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Radio program on scientific vocations, 1946
  - Teacher sponsor scholarships, 1947-1965
  - Exhibit contest, 1948-1949
  - Science club reports, 1948-1949
  - VJAS Constitution, c.1950
  - VJAS Committee of VAS--Reports, 1956-1960
  - VJAS Committee of VAS--Minutes, etc., 1959
  - VJAS history--Thelma J. Heatwole, 1960-1961
  - Minutes, agendas, and miscellaneous, 1960-1961
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1960-1961
  - Miscellaneous files, 1960-1961
  - Judges for VJAS exhibits, 1962
  - Meeting at Lexington, 1961
  - New business, 1961-1962
  - Miscellaneous files, 1961-1964
  - Meeting at Norfolk, 1962
  - National Science Seminars, 1962-1963
  - Information on creating a VJAS brochure, 1962-1963
  - Attendance at the AAAS meetings, 1962-1968
  - Meeting at Roanoke, 1963
  - VJAS affiliation with the National Science Foundation, 1963-1975
  - Visiting Scientist Program, 1963-1976
  - List of VJAS affiliated clubs, 1963-1979
  - Educational materials, 1964
  - Meeting at Charlottesville, 1964
  - Meeting at Charlottesville--Awards, 1964
  - Miscellaneous files, 1964-1965
- Records, 1964-1979 (Bulk 1964-1966) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous files, including meeting at Richmond, 1964-1965
  - VJAS committee of VAS, 1964-1965
  - Information on Virginia Junior Science, Humanities, and Engineering, 1964-1965
  - National Science Teachers Association--Information on Science Conferences, 1964-1967
  - Science Services, Inc. and Science Clubs of America, 1964-1970
  - Grant No. GE-4281, 1965
  - Meeting at Richmond, 1965
  - Photos of the meeting at Richmond, 1965
  - Miscellaneous files, 1965
  - VJAS Committee of VAS, 1965-1966
  - Research Committee, 1965-1967
  - Virginia High School League requesting calendar of events from VJAS, 1965-1970
  - Certificates and citations--Blank forms, 1965-1975
  - VJAS information on AAAS, 1956-1979
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting at Harrisonburg, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting--Awards, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting--Correspondence, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting--Invitations and badges, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting--Key rings, 1966
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary meeting--Regrets to invitations, 1966
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1966-1967
  - Grant GW-1129, 1967.
- Records, 1966-1979 (Bulk 1966-1970) (Box 3)
  - Letters from high schools requesting VJAS films, 1966-1967
  - Virginia Talent Search information and programs, 1966-1979
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1967
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1967-1968
  - Research Grant Committee, 1967-1968
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1968
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1968
  - R. C. Berry Chemistry Award, 1968
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1968-1969
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1968-1969
  - Miscellaneous files and clippings, 1968-1969
  - VJAS research grants, 1968-1969
  - Distinguished Service Awards, 1968-1970
  - List of judges for VJAS, 1968-1970
  - Letters of gratitude to people who gave presentations at VJAS events, 1968-1979
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1969
  - Miscellaneous files--M. B. Rowe, 1969-1970
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1969-1970
  - Newspaper clippings, 1969-1970
  - VJAS research grants, 1969-1970
  - Scrapbook, 1969-1973
- Records, 1970-1979 (Bulk 1970-1973) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1970
  - Student follow-ups--Newspaper Articles, 1970
  - Revisions for VJAS Handbook, 1970
  - E. C. L. Miller Award, 1970-1971
  - Meeting at Richmond, 1970-1971
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1970-1971
  - Miscellaneous files--M. B. Rowe, 1970-1971
  - Research grant records, 1970-1971
  - Meeting at Blacksburg, 1971
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1971
  - List of public and private schools, division and science superintendents, and VJAS committee members, 1971
  - Research grant materials, 1971-1972
  - VJAS budget, 1971-1972
  - VJAS Committee notes and papers, 1971-1972
  - VJAS Committee members, 1971-1979
  - Vouchers, requests for checks, and financial reports, 1971-1980
  - Meeting at the Natural Bridge, 1972
  - Miscellaneous files--E. L. Wisman, 1972
  - Research grant records, 1972
  - Invoices paid, 1972
  - Miscellaneous files, 1972-1973
  - Miscellaneous files--L. S. Anthony, 1973
  - Minutes and papers from the Annual Meeting, 1973
  - Invoices paid, 1973
- Records, 1973-1980 (Box 5)
  - Meetings at Williamsburg and Norfolk, 1973-1974
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1973-1974
  - Photos from the meeting at Norfolk, 1974
  - Research grants, 1974
  - VJAS awards, 1974
  - Miscellaneous files, 1974-1975
  - VJAS Committee of VAS, 1974-1975
  - Pre-registration information for the annual meeting, 1974-1978
  - Meeting at Harrionsburg, 1975
  - Miscellaneous files--A. W. Burke, 1975
  - Invoices paid, 1975
  - VJAS Committee of VAS, 1975-1976
  - Meeting at Fairfax, 1976
  - Photographs and negatives of the VJAS Annual Meeting, 1936
  - Invoices paid, 1976
  - Organization of readers for VJAS papers, 1976-1978
  - Fundraising for VJAS, 1976-1980
  - Duties and work schedule for VJAS Committee members, 1977
  - Thirty sixth Annual VJAS Meeting, 1977
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1977-1978
  - Thirty seventh Annual VJAS Meeting, 1978
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1978-1979
  - Annual Meeting, 1979
  - Miscellaneous files--A. B. Niemeyer, Jr., 1979
  - Miscellaneous files--V. B. Remsburg, 1979-1980
  - Miscellaneous files--A. B. Niemeyer, Jr., 1980
- Records, 1980-1997, undated (Box 6)
  - January 62 Meeting of VJAS, 1980
  - Annual Meeting and miscellaneous information, 1980
  - VJAS Award winners, 1980
  - Donor list of the VJAS, 1980
  - Invoices paid, 1980
  - Winter and Summer VJAS meetings, 1981
  - List of VJAS student who have presented papers at annual meetings, 1981
  - VJAS Committee of VAS, 1981-1982
  - Letters and lists of possible donors of VJAS, 1981-1985
  - January 23 meeting of VJAS, 1982
  - April 20-22 meeting at Virginia Tech, 1982
  - Summer meeting at Peaks of Otter, 1982
  - Invoices paid, 1983
  - American Junior Academy of Science Annual Conference papers, 1983-1984
  - Minutes and papers from the July 21 VJAS meeting at Graves Mountain Lodge,1984
  - Scholarship information awarded by the VJAS, 1984
  - Scholarship information awarded by the VJAS, 1984
  - Minutes of meetings and lists of VJAS Committee members, 1984
  - Invoices paid, 1984
  - Letters of invitation to the VJAS Sponsor's reception, 1984-1985
  - Miscellaneous newspaper articles, 1984-1986
  - Information and agendas for VJAS meetings, 1985
  - Invoices paid, 1985
  - VJAS Section Awards, 1986
  - Information about Astronaut Robert A. Parker speaking to the VAS and VJAS at the annual meeting, 1986
  - Invoices paid, 1986
  - Papers on the winner of the Frances and Sydney Lewis Environmental Science Scholarship, 1987
  - Special Award Nominations and winners, 1987
  - Nominations for the VJAS Sponsor Award, 1987
  - Section Award Forms, 1987
  - Information about VJAS Meetings, 1987
  - Student applications for the Frances and Sydney Lewis Environmental Science Scholarship, 1987
  - Invoices paid, 1987
  - Nominations for the Science Club Award and the VAS Science Teacher Award, 1987-1988
  - Special Awards Nominations, 1988
  - Papers from the Section Awards, 1988
  - Letters to and from Dr. Dean Decker, Director of the VJAS, 1988
  - Applications from students applying for the Frances and Sydney Lewis Environmental Science Scholarship, 1988
  - Invoices paid, 1988
  - Invoices paid, 1989
  - History of VJAS and "Fifty Years of VJAS," 1991
  - Awards script, 1991
  - "Galaxies in Collision" by Debra Meloy Elmgreen--The first George W. Jeffers Memorial Lecture, 1992
  - Information about registration to attend the VJAS awards ceremony at James Madison University, 1994
  - Letter for VJAS membership, 1994
  - Annual meeting information and registration, 1995
  - Annual meeting information and registration, 1996
  - Annual meeting information and registration, 1997
  - Junior Science Bulletin, 1952-1979
  - "Characterization of Junior Academy of Science Participation"
  - "Award of Honor" certificates.
  - Science Supervisors Superintendents.
  - Periodic table.
  - Biographical and VJAS information about Edgar V. Russell, Jr.--Photograph also included.
  - Listing of VJAS Committee members, officers, and other members.
  - "VJAS Hall of Fame" general revision.
- Publications, 1963-1993 (Box 7)
  - The Virginia Junior Academy of Science Proceedings,1963-1993
    - Volumes 1-24, 1963-1986
    - Volumes 26-31, 1988-1993
- Publications and Records, 1942-1992, undated (Box 8)
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Handbook
    - 1963
    - 1965-1966
    - 1968
    - 1970
    - 1972
    - 1975
    - 1977
    - 1980?
    - 1982?
    - 1987
    - 1992
  - "History of the VJAS" as presented at the 50th Anniversary Meeting of the VAS. The slides and narration were prepared by Vera Remsburg,1942-1973
  - Pictures taken of members of the VJAS Committee Meetings --Judges, recipients of awards, etc.,1975
  - Strip of photographic film possibly of the 1976 VJAS Summer meeting at Peaks of Otter.
  - "VJAS in Action"--Four filmstrips.
  - "Story of the VJAS"--Slides.
  - Two card holders of the 30th Anniversary of the VJAS.
  - Two key chains of the 25th Anniversary of the VJAS.
  - Three souvenir T-shirts of the 50th Anniversary of the VJAS.
  - Souvenir pencil of the 50th Anniversary of the VJAS.
- Publications and Records, 1970-1990, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Adult and Student Forms, Philadelphia, 1986 (Box-folder 9-1)
  - AJAS/AAAS Annual Meeting, Los Angeles, 1985 (Box-folder 9-2)
  - Annual Meeting Programs (1971 and 1974) (Box-folder 9-3)
  - Annual Meeting Programs (1983 and 1985) (Box-folder 9-4)
  - Annual Meeting Programs (1986 and 1987) (Box-folder 9-5)
  - Annual Meeting Programs (1988-1990) (Box-folder 9-6)
  - Applications (Box-folder 9-7)
  - Award of Honor Certificate (Box-folder 9-8)
  - Banquet Booklet (1985) (Box-folder 9-9)
  - Chairs (Box-folder 9-10)
  - Charter Certificate (Box-folder 9-11)
  - Commission Task Force (Box-folder 9-12)
  - Directories, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 9-13)
  - D.O.E (1988 UVA VJAS Annual Meeting) (Box-folder 9-14)
  - Election Slate, 1987, 1989 (Box-folder 9-15)
  - General Program Schedule, 1985 (Box-folder 9-16)
  - Golden Anniversary Meeting Letterhead Paper, 1973 (Box-folder 9-17)
  - Handbooks (1970 and 1974) (Box-folder 9-18)
  - Handbooks (1975, 1977, and n.d.) (Box-folder 9-19)
  - Housing (Box-folder 9-20)
  - Jr. Committee (Box-folder 9-21)
  - Junior Science Bulletin (v. 20, no. 1,2), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 9-22)
  - Names and Addresses (Box-folder 9-23)
  - PA Junior Academy of Science 40th State Meeting Handbook, 1974 (Box-folder 9-24)
  - Paper Readers (Box-folder 9-25)
  - Photos (Box-folder 9-26)
  - Proposed Budget for 1985-1987 (Box-folder 9-27)
  - VAS Ballots and Envelopes (Box-folder 9-28)
  - VJAS Affiliate Your School Letters, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 9-29)
  - VJAS Annual Meeting Info, Chicago, 1987 (Box-folder 9-30)
  - VJAS Booklet (Box-folder 9-31)
  - VJAS Correspondence (Box-folder 9-32)
  - VJAS Friends Letters (Box-folder 9-33)
  - VJAS General Info (Box-folder 9-34)
  - VJAS Meeting Agenda, Graves Mt. Lodge, 1986 (Box-folder 9-35)
  - VJAS Membership Cards (Box-folder 9-36)
  - VJAS Member Certificates (Box-folder 9-37)
  - VJAS Member Letters, 1984, 1985, 1987 (Box-folder 9-38)
  - VJAS Member Letters from Election Committee, 1989, 1990 (Box-folder 9-39)
  - VJAS Video Tape Script (Box-folder 9-40)
  - VJAS 1983 Meeting at GMU, 1983 (Box-folder 9-41)
  - VJAS 1984 Meeting at the University of Richmond, 1984 (Box-folder 9-42)
  - VJAS 1986 Meeting at JMU, 1986 (Box-folder 9-43)
  - VAS 1987 Meeting at ODU, 1987 (Box-folder 9-44)
  - VAS 1989 Meeting at VCU, 1989 (Box-folder 9-45)
  - VAS 1990 Meeting at GMU, 1990 (Box-folder 9-46)
  - William and Mary Papers (Box-folder 9-47)
- Publications and Scrapbooks,1971-1986, n.d. (Box 10)
  - Proceedings of the Virginia Junior Academy of Science
    - Volume 1, Roanoke, Virginia, May 1963
    - Volume 2, Charlottesville, Virginia, May 1964
    - Volume 3, Richmond, Virginia, May 1965
    - Volume 4, Harrisonburg, Virginia, May 1966
    - Volume 5, Norfolk, Virginia, May 1967
    - Volume 6, Roanoke, Virginia, May 1968
    - Volume 7, Fredericksburg, Virginia, May 1969
    - Volume 8, Richmond, Virginia, May 1970
    - Volume 9, Blacksburg, Virginia, May 1971
    - Volume 10, Lexington, Virginia, May 1972
    - Volume 11, Williamsburg, Virginia, May 1973
    - Volume 12, Norfolk, Virginia, May 1974
    - Volume 13, Harrisonburg, Virginia, May 1975
    - Volume 14, Fairfax, Virginia, May 1976
    - Volume 15, Petersburg, Virginia, May 1977
    - Volume 16, Blacksburg, Virginia, May 1978
    - Volume 17, Richmond, Virginia, May 1979
    - Volume 18, Richmond, Virginia, May 1980
    - Volume 19, Norfolk, Virginia, May 1981
    - Volume 20, Blacksburg, Virginia, April 1982
    - Volume 21, Fairfax, Virginia, May 1983
    - Volume 22, Richmond, Virginia, May 1984
    - Volume 23, Williamsburg, Virginia, May 1985
    - Volume 24, Harrisonburg, Virginia, May 1986
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Program, VPI&SU, April 20-22, 1982
  - Directory and Proceedings, Association of Science, 1970-1971
  - Binder of Virginia Academy of Science Correspondence, 1982-1985
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1976-1977
- Scrapbooks, 1975-1984 (Box 11)
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1975-1976
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1977-1978
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1979
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1980-1981
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1981-1982
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1982-1983
  - Virginia Junior Academy of Science Scrapbook, 1983-1984
- Materials displayed at the 25th anniversary meeting, 1966 (Folder 1)
- Poster from 30th anniversary meeting, 1971 (Folder 1)